A schema change rarely fails where it is written.
It fails downstream, in a dashboard, join, contract,
or sensitive-data control.
LineageProof turns DataHub context into a reviewable
decision before a migration ships.
The input names one DataHub dataset and records each
field before and after the change.
This example renames a monetary field, relaxes
nullability, and removes a sensitive address.
Invalid or incomplete manifests stop before any tool
call.
The agent first reads entity identity, ownership, and
the current schema.
For every changed field, it then retrieves downstream
lineage and observed query context.
Eight read calls form the evidence chain for this
three-field scenario.
This is the verified public fixture run.
It needs no credentials and sends nothing outside the
machine.
The command returns request remediation and writes a
JSON audit, human remediation plan, S A R I F, hashed
receipts, and a write-back preview.
The decision is request remediation.
A field identity change reaches downstream assets,
nullable data conflicts with observed use, a type
change violates a query contract, and sensitive data
reaches a target without matching classification.
Each finding points to the exact receipt sequence used
as evidence.
Receipts keep the tool name, non-secret arguments,
sequence number, and response hash.
Raw DataHub responses, credentials, and account data
are not copied into the public record.
The human plan is not a generic warning.
It proposes compatibility fields or a versioned
migration, explicit null semantics and backfill,
downstream contract tests, owner notification, and
approved classification propagation before deploy.
The audit produces a deterministic mutation plan, but
the plan states dry run true and mutation tools
invoked false.
It is bound to the exact audit-report hash, so a
modified plan cannot quietly inherit the report's
evidence.
Write-back is a separate command.
It checks that every required mutation tool is
available, allowlists add tags and update description,
caps execution at one hundred calls, and requires both
apply and an acknowledgement equal to the audited
change ID.
The public mutation proof exercises one tag call and
four description updates against a synthetic fixture.
Its receipt says external metadata modified false.
A future live response would remain unverified until
an independent read-back proves the target state.
Fourteen tests cover the decision rules, deterministic
outputs, mutation gates, and tamper rejection.
The release verifier checks eight read receipts, five
synthetic mutation receipts, and every public text
file for privacy leaks.
LineageProof makes schema-change review reproducible,
explainable, and safe by default.
A reviewer can see what changed, which DataHub
evidence matters, why the change is blocked, and
exactly what did and did not happen.